Guide to the Mary E. Gawthorpe Papers TAM.275
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: Correspondence, 1930-1973; 61471
  - Pankhurst, Sylvia, 1932-1935; 61531 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Paul, Alice, 1929-1931; 61530 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Penny, Frank, undated, 1915-1929; 61529 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Pethick-Lawrence, Emmeline, 1931-1935; 61528 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Pomeroy, Ella, undated, 1929-1932; 61527 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Post, Hermann, undated, 1932-1933; 61526 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - R, undated, 1917-1933, 1970; 61525 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Reid, Helen Rogers, 1925-1931; 61524 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Reiner, Edith, 1929; 61523 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Rigby, Edith, undated, 1932-1951; 61522 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Robins, Elizabeth, 1931; 61521 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Rowe, Frances, 1917; 61520 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Russell, Ada, 1936-1944; 61519 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Russell, Bertrand, 1932, 1970; 61518 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Russell, Ethel, 1942-1945; 61517 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Russell, Hilda, 1920-1939; 61516 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Russell, Jessie, 1947-1951; 61515 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Russell, Marie Valentine, 1916-1927; 61514 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - S, undated, 1916-1933; 61513 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sadow, Sue, 1932-1933; 61512 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Sanders, John, undated; 61511 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Sanders, John, 1921-1929; 61510 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sanders, John, 1930-1939; 61509 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sanders, John, 1940-1949; 61508 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Sanders, John, 1950-1959; 61507 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Sanders, John, 1960-1963; 61506 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Schulkind, Adelaide, 1929-1932; 61505 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Scott, Charles Prestwich, 1910, 1931; 61504 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Scudder, Vida D., 1932; 61503 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Sharp, Doris, 1931; 61502 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Shaw, George Bernard, 1912, 1933; 61501 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Shelby, Gertrude Mathews, 1921-1926; 61500 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Singleton, Caroline, 1926-1928; 61499 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Smith, B.A., 1915-1928; 61498 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Smith, Jessica, 1968-1969; 61497 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Stevens, Doris, 1928-1931; 61496 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Storm, Diana, 1928-1931; 61495 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Strang, Lewis C., 1927; 61494 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Sullivan, William L., 1921; 61493 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Swanwick, Helena, 1908, 1932; 61492 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Swayne, Blanche, 1932-1933; 61491 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - T, undated, 1919-1933; 61490 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Tolson, Chas. G., 1909; 61489 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Tone, Franchot, undated, 1930, 1968; 61488 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Tone, Gertrude Franchot, undated, 1919-1923; 61487 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Tone, Gertrude Franchot, 1924-1938; 61486 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Unity Society, 1929; 61485 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Upward, Allen, 1913; 61484 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Valiant, Grace, 1928-1930; 61483 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Verrall, Richard P. and Gertrude, 1919-1921; 61482 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - W, 1915-1931, 1966, 1970-1972; 61481 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Ward, Annie Gawthorpe, undated, 1913-1921, 1948; 61480 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Ward, Sidney John, 1910, 1929; 61479 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Ward, Stella Crossley, undated, 1930-1933; 61478 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Watson, Elizabeth, undated, 1926-1933; 61477 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - WEVD, undated, 1931; 61476 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - White, Eliot, 1931-1933; 61475 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Wiener, Paul Lester, 1929; 61474 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Woman Suffrage Party, Brooklyn, 1916; 61473 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Z, 1933; 61472 (Box 4, Folder 51)
- Series III: Subject Files, 1881-1990; 61352
  The subject files cover the period from 1881 to Gawthorpe's death in 1973 (with most files dating from 1907 to 1913), as well as materials relating to Gawthorpe's estate up until 1990. The earlier material relates to the WSPU, including Gawthorpe's work in the North of England, as well as a range of other pro- and anti-suffrage organizations. This series extensively covers two of Gawthorpe's initiatives in 1912: her coordination of a petition against the forcible feeding of suffragette prisoners and her call for a national women's hunger strike. The petition drive generated responses from a range of figures, including Havelock Ellis and George Bernard Shaw, which are included in the subject file.
  - Actress Suffrage Organizations, 1909-1910; 61470 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Adult Suffrage Society, 1907; 61469 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, 1920; 61468 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Artists' Suffrage League, undated; 61467 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Bangs, Jean M., 1931-1933; 61466 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Biographical Materials: John Sanders, Jr., 1922-1933; 61465 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Biographical Materials: Mary Gawthorpe, 1881-1937; 61464 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Biographical Materials: Mary Gawthorpe, 1962-1990; 61463 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1916, 1947-1950; 61462 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Catt, Carrie Chapman: Speeches, 1911, 1916; 61461 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Central Society for Women's Suffrage, undated; 61460 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Clippings: General, undated, 1912-1968; 61459 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Conciliation Committee for Women's Suffrage, 1910; 61458 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Davison, Emily Wilding, 1913; 61457 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Education Issues: Pamphlets, 1910-1913; 61456 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Ephemera: Programs, Invitations, Notes, undated, 1906-1938; 61455 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fabian News, 1911-1912; 61454 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fabian Society: Pamphlets, 1907-1912; 61453 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Family: General, undated, 1937, 1941; 61452 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Forcible Feeding: Clippings, 1912; 61451 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Forcible Feeding: Shaw Clippings, 1912; 61450 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Forcible Feeding Petition: Correspondence, 1912; 61449 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Forcible Feeding Petition: Organizing Materials, 1912; 61448 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Freewoman, undated; 61447 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Friends of India, 1932; 61446 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Garland, Charles: Clippings, undated, 1922-1929; 61445 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Garland Fund (American Fund for Public Service): Reports and Clippings, 1923-1934; 61444 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Garland, Marie Tudor: Clippings, undated, 1916-1931; 61443 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Hardie, Keir: Suffrage Pamphlets, undated, 1905; 61442 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Hunger Strike: Clippings, 1912-1913; 61441 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Hunger Strike: Correspondence, 1912; 61440 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Hunger Strike: Editorials, 1912-1913; 61439 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Hunger Strike: Letters to the Editor, 1912-1913; 61438 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Illness: Baylis House, undated, 1913; 61437 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Illness: Mary Gawthorpe Testimonial Fund, 1911; 61436 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Illness: Support from suffragists, 1915-1916; 61435 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Independent Labour Party: Pamphlets, undated, 1900-1906; 61434 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Independent Labour Party: Suffrage Materials, 1906; 61433 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - International Women's Franchise Club, undated, 1910; 61432 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Labour Organizations: Leaflets, undated, 1910; 61431 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Lancashire and Cheshire Women's Textile and Other Workers' Representation Committee, undated; 61430 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Leeds: General, 1906-1908; 61429 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Leeds Women's Suffrage Society, 1906; 61428 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Liberal Organizations, undated, 1907-1909; 61427 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Liberal Women's Suffrage League, undated; 61426 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Manchester: General, undated, 1908-1910; 61425 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Men's League for Opposing Women's Suffrage, ca.1909; 61424 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Men's League for Women's Suffrage, 1907-1909; 61423 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Men's suffrage organizations, undated, 1909-1911; 61422 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Merseles, Theodore F., 1929; 61421 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - National Committee to Promote the Break Up of the Poor Law, 1910; 61420 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - National Union of Societies for Equal Citizenship, 1923; 61419 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - National Union of Women Workers, 1908; 61418 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies, undated, 1909; 61417 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Nearing, Scott, 1916, 1931; 61416 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - New Freewoman, 1913; 61415 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - New School for Social Research, 1930-1932; 61414 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - New York, Journey to: MG, 1915-1916; 61413 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - New York State Woman Suffrage Party, 1916; 61412 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - North of England Society for Women's Suffrage, 1908-1909; 61411 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Old Time Players, 1929; 61410 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Pankhurst and Pethick-Lawrence Trial: Clippings, 1912; 61409 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Pankhurst, Sylvia, undated, 1931-1932; 61408 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Pankhurst, Sylvia: The Suffragette Movement, undated, 1931, 1936; 61407 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Pankhurst, Sylvia: The Suffragette Movement Correspondence, 1931-1932; 61406 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Pankhurst, Sylvia: Woodford Nursery School Committee, 1930; 61405 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Pankhursts: Clippings, undated, 1925-1932; 61404 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons, 1910; 61403 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Russells: Clippings, undated, 1914; 61402 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Sanders, John, Jr.: Condolence Cards, 1963; 61401 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Sanders, John, Jr.: Condolence Letters, 1963; 61400 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Sanders, John, Jr.: General, 1921-1922, 1934; 61399 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Scott, Charles Prestwich, 1929-1932; 61398 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Shaw, George Bernard, 1909, 1931; 61397 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Sims, George R.: "The Cry of the Children" (Tribune Extras Pamphlet), undated; 61396 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Speaking Engagements: MG, 1907-1910, 1919; 61395 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Suffragette Fellowship, 1932, 1968-1972; 61394 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Suffragette Split: Clippings, 1912; 61393 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Suffragists' Vigilance League, 1909; 61392 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sweated Industries Exhibition, 1906; 61391 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Union Francaise Pour le Suffrage des Femmes, 1909; 61390 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Upward, Allen, 1910, 1926; 61389 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Votes for Women, 1909; 61388 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - War Resisters' International, 1926; 61387 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Webb, Sidney and Beatrice: Course of Lectures, 1910-1911; 61386 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Women Writers' Suffrage League, undated; 61385 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Women's Freedom League, 1907-1909; 61384 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Women's International Matteotti Committee, 1932-1933; 61383 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Women's Labor League, 1905-1906; 61382 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Women's National Anti-Suffrage League, 1908; 61381 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Aberdeen, 1908; 61380 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Birmingham, undated, 1910; 61379 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Bradford, undated, 1908; 61378 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Dundee, 1908; 61377 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Glasgow, 1910; 61376 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Kensington, 1907-1911; 61375 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Lambeth, undated; 61374 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Leeds, undated, 1907-1908; 61373 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Liverpool, 1909; 61372 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Manchester, undated, 1908-1910; 61371 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, National, undated; 61370 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, National, 1906-1907; 61369 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, National, 1907-1908; 61368 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, National: Leaflets, 1909; 61367 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, National: Women's Exhibition, 1909; 61366 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, National, 1910-1911; 61365 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Preston, 1908-1909; 61364 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Rawtenstall, 1908; 61363 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Scottish, 1908; 61362 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Southport, 1908-1910; 61361 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Women's Social and Political Union, Wimbledon, 1908-1911; 61360 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Women's Suffrage: Clippings, undated, 1908-1975; 61359 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Women's Suffrage: Leaflets, undated, 1906-1911; 61358 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Women's Suffrage: Pamphlets, undated, 1906-1914; 61357 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Women's Suffrage: United States, 1916; 61356 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Women's Suffrage Crisis: Clippings, 1913; 61355 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Women's Suffrage Society: Blackpool and Fylde, 1909; 61354 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Writings: MG, 1908, 1912; 61353 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Series IV: Educational Materials and Notes, circa 1890-1932; 61339
  This series covers Gawthorpe's training and career as a teacher from 1898 to 1904, her notes and travels during 1914 through 1916 following the end of her involvement in the WSPU, and her study materials from 1916 when she arrived in the United States.
  - Course Materials: London and Northern Tutorial College, circa 1890; 61351 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Italy: Notes and Materials, 1914-1915; 61350 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Notes: Miscellaneous, undated; 61349 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Regulations for the Training of Teachers, 1913; 61348 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Secretarial Training: Kensington College, 1915; 61347 (Box 6, Folder 46-47)
  - Sketchbooks, undated, 1932; 61346 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Study Notes: History of the United States, 1916; 61345 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Teaching Materials, 1899; 61344 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Teaching Materials: Cockburn School, circa 1899; 61343 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Teaching Materials: Elementary Syllabus, 1903-1904; 61342 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Teaching Materials: Leeds School Board, 1898; 61341 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - University of Kansas, 1916; 61340 (Box 6, Folder 54)
- Series V: Postcards, 1903-1970; 61337
  Arrangement
  Postcards from Garrs to Gawthorpe's mother are filed chronologically in the General section.
  This series contains postcards received and/or collected by Gawthorpe. The series is divided into two sections, Suffrage and General. Of note in this series is the only material in the collection that reflects Gawthorpe's relationship with Tom Garrs.
  - Postcard Binder 1: Suffrage and General, 1903-1917, undated; 61338 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Postcard Binder 2: General, 1907-1911; 477002 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Postcard Binder 3: General, 1912-1931; 477003 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Postcard Binder 4: General, 1931-1970; 477004 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Series VI: Photographs, Graphic Materials, and Artifacts, 1900-circa 1950s; 476825
  This series contains photographs, negatives, graphic materials, and artifacts, many of which are personal in nature. The photographs are mostly images of Gawthorpe, her family and friends, and a variety of buildings, landmarks, and landscapes, taken during various vacations and trips. Most photographs originate from albums presumably created by Gawthorpe and have descriptive information written on the back (the negatives from these albums are also included). To a lesser extent, the photographic materials depict British suffragette leaders and lesser-known suffragists wearing clothing with pro-suffrage slogans or otherwise engaged in activities in support of the movement.
  Graphic materials consist of oversize programs, flyers, and leaflets related to the suffrage movement. An article on the forcible feeding of suffrage prisoners is also included. Other graphic materials include reproductive prints of religious scenes and various other subjects.
  Most of the artifacts are personal effects, including tarot cards, a calling card case, a cigarette holder, an engraved fountain pen, human hair (likely Gawthorpe's), and other items. However, there is also an apron with a pro-suffrage slogan and other artifacts from the women's suffrage movement.
  - Artifacts: Case, Mirror, Pen, and Tarot Cards, circa 1957, undated; 478372 (Box 9)
  - Artifacts: Gloves, Ribbon, and "Self Denial" Sash, 1906, undated; 478373 (Box 10)
  - Artifacts: "Self Denial" Sash, undated; 478374 (Box 11)
  - Birthday Card, undated; 478371 (Box 9)
  - Gawthorpe Family and Extended Family, 1906-1931, undated; 476827 (Box A004, Folder 1)
  - Gawthorpe, Mary, 1900-1921, undated; 476828 (Box A004, Folder 2)
  - Gawthorpe Reception at Tamiment Library, 2004; 477111 (Box MSOS002, Folder 1)
  - Gawthorpe-Sanders Home, Whitestone Landing (Long Island, NY), 1921; 476829 (Box A004, Folder 3)
  - General/Unidentified, 1916-1925, undated; 476835 (Box A004, Folder 4)
  - General/Unidentified (includes Victor Grayson), 1902-1914, undated; 476834 (Box A004, Folder 5)
  - Graphic Materials: General, 1909, undated; 476838 (Box A004, Folder 6)
  - Pankhurst, Emmeline and Christabel, Sylvia and Richard, 1931, undated; 476831 (Box A004, Folder 7)
  - Printed Ephemera, 1907-1931, undated; 477112 (Box MSXOS001)
  - Printed Ephemera: Suffrage, 1907-1912; 477001 (Box MSOS002, Folder 2)
  - Printed Ephemera: Suffrage, 1908-1912, undated; 477113 (Flat-file-folder 8)
  - Photograph Albums (with Negatives), circa 1930s-1950s; 477000 (Box 8)
  - Suffrage, General (includes Elizabeth Robbins and Charlotte Despard), 1908-1917, undated; 476832 (Box A004, Folder 8)